so we will come back to hyperparameter tuning and model
selection, but now that we have more tools, more concepts to understand these
we will see it again, so the main question is can we compute, can we verify
this, can we see if there is a difference between the real risk and the empirical
risk, but we don't have the real data distribution: that's the main problem, and
the validation set and the test set will be quantities that will estimate this distribution
and the training set will be used to find the model that will minimize the
empirical risk, so I don't want to rely on this estimation of this quantity
because you see that h_S is the optimal point to minimize L_S and of course there
is a h_D that will be the optimal model that will minimize L_D, but since we don't
have D we cannot find it, but we will simulate it, we will use another set
called validation set for hyperparameters, that we will use to estimate
this quantity, and if the gap between the two is huge
probably the gap between the real risk and this quantity is also important and
so if you deploy your model the performance that you will observe will
probably be closer to the performance on the validation set
than the one that you obtained by choosing the model that minimized the empirical
risk and so the validation set is defined similarly than the
training set and the loss is computed exactly in the same way, you use the same
loss function and you take the empirical average over the set V
and since we have an iterative algorithm for the optimization, you will monitor
the two values, you will monitor the empirical risk in red, which we will call
the training error, and you will monitor an estimation of the risk with
the validation set, that we will call after that the validation error and this
is typically the shape of the two curves that you will observe in many of your
experiments in deep learning, at the beginning the model is
performing badly on the two sets, and at some point you will see the curve of the
validation error that will increase: it means that at this point the model
begins to memorize, to cheat, to use features that are only relevant in the
training set to minimize the loss and so it will continue to decrease but these
features are not useful to generalize and so the validation error will
increase and what we probably want to do is to do several check points around this
curve, so you will save the model parameters on your disk and you will
stop the training before the validation error increases too much it's called
early stopping and so you retrieve the model parameters evaluated here instead
of retrieving the parameters only at the end of the training, and if we come back
to our experimental protocol now I can define several model families, so maybe a
one layer neural network, a two layer neural network, a convolutional neural
network, etc. I will define different families of models, each family will have
a set of parameters where the optimizer will navigate inside and I will find for
each family, the model inside the space H that will minimize the empirical
risk predictor here, and then I will evaluate each of these models on my
validation set to retrieve the performance, to retrieve
an estimation of the risk and so this one has the best performance on my
validation set and again maybe because I'm optimizing, I'm looking for the best
model according to the validation set over many many experiments maybe I can
still overfit the validation set it's more tricky to understand but it can
happen, I will use a final test set to be sure that the performance here is close
to the performance here, if there is a huge gap then there may be a
problem in your experimental protocol you should investigate more, so the
take-home message of this presentation is that machine learning is very broad
there's a lot of different techniques, different models, different algorithms in
machine learning, the statistical learning framework helps us to
understand more what is overfitting in terms of a probability distribution
defined over the examples, a model can be too biased, too simple, not enough complexity
or can have too much variance where there's a lot of complexity but because
I don't have enough data, the decision boundaries are arbitrary, and we saw that
data is necessary but not sufficient, and finally deep learning is a very
efficient way to define complex hypothesis classes and we don't know
still the answer, but deep learning empirically generalizes better than
other models and this is a very active research topic today to understand why
these architectures minimize the gap between the empirical risk and the real
risk, and here I put some references so that you can have the math, but done
properly, it would have required more than one hour to cover these concepts, but I
used these books to to inspire myself for this talk, thank
you very much